Today, how about binge-watching?
오늘 정주행으로 몰아보기 어때요?
Lying in bed and binge-watching TV dramas has become a common daily habit for many of us.
침대에 누워 드라마를 몰아보는 일은 이제 흔한 일상이 되었습니다.
Have you ever said just one more episode and then ended up staying awake all night?
"한 화만 더 봐야지" 하다가 결국 밤을 새워본 적이 있으신가요?
The auto-play button on streaming platforms acts as a powerful temptation for our human brain.
넷플릭스의 자동 재생 버튼은 우리의 뇌를 강력하게 유혹합니다.
Studies show that over seventy percent of adults worldwide regularly enjoy binge-watching their favorite shows.
전 세계 성인의 약 70퍼센트 이상이 몰아보기를 즐긴다고 답했습니다.
From a medical perspective, how does this habit physically impact our entire body?
의학적인 관점에서 몰아보기는 우리 몸에 어떤 영향을 미칠까요?
Today, we will dissect the scientific effects of binge-watching on both your body and mind.
오늘 우리는 몰아보기가 몸과 마음에 미치는 영향을 파헤쳐 보겠습니다.
That comfortable-looking sofa can actually turn out to be a hidden enemy for your spine.
편안해 보이는 소파는 사실 우리 뼈와 근육의 적이 될 수 있습니다.
Watching flashing screens in a dark room is the main culprit for extreme eye fatigue.
어두운 방에서 번쩍이는 화면은 눈의 피로를 극대화하는 주범입니다.
Inside our brain, an enormous cascade of chemicals is being released without a single pause.
우리의 뇌 속에서는 엄청난 화학물질이 쉴 새 없이 쏟아지고 있죠.
Is binge-watching truly a serious danger that ruins our overall physical and mental health?
몰아보기는 정말 우리 건강을 심각하게 망치는 주범일까요?
Let us dissect this modern habit with medical facts and clear illustrations.
의학적 팩트와 친근한 일러스트로 이 현상을 낱낱이 해부해 봅니다.
Now, let us follow the map of biological changes caused by continuous screen viewing.
지금부터 몰아보기가 만드는 신체 변화의 지도를 함께 따라가 보시죠.
When you start binge-watching, the reward pathways in your brain immediately light up with activity.
몰아보기를 시작하면 뇌의 보상 회로가 활발하게 작동하기 시작합니다.
A pleasure-inducing chemical called dopamine begins to flood your brain like a sudden rushing wave.
쾌락의 호르몬인 '도파민'이 뇌 속에서 홍수처럼 분비되는 것입니다.
Curiosity about the next episode continuously stimulates this ongoing release of rewarding dopamine signals.
다음 이야기에 대한 호기심이 도파민 분비를 끊임없이 촉진하죠.
Since the next episode plays automatically, your brain experiences instant gratification without any effort.
손가락 하나 움직이지 않아도 다음 화면이 나오니 멈출 수 없습니다.
This neurological cycle is highly similar to the behavioral patterns seen in mild substance addictions.
이러한 신경학적 자극은 가벼운 약물 중독과 매우 유사한 패턴입니다.
Vibrant visual displays and stereo sound systems strongly capture your sensory attention for hours.
화려한 화면과 입체 음향은 시각과 청각을 강력하게 사로잡습니다.
Under this heavy flood of dopamine, we completely lose track of time and environment.
도파민의 홍수 속에서 우리는 시간 감각을 완전히 잃어버리게 됩니다.
The brain craves more shocking twists and continuously demands higher levels of chemical stimulation.
뇌는 더 자극적인 반전을 원하며 계속해서 도파민을 요구합니다.
However, when the series finally ends, this dopamine production comes to a sudden halt.
하지만 마침내 드라마가 모두 끝나면 도파민 분비는 급격히 멈춥니다.
The sudden emptiness felt at this point is called post-binge watching depression by psychologists.
이 순간 밀려오는 깊은 공허함을 '포스트 몰아보기 우울증'이라 부릅니다.
This down-depression occurs because your overstimulated dopamine receptors become temporarily numbed and unresponsive.
과도하게 자극받았던 도파민 수용체들이 무뎌진 결과입니다.
The previous excitement quickly vanishes, replaced by sudden irritability, exhaustion, and mental fatigue.
즐거웠던 기분은 순식간에 가라앉고 심한 짜증과 피로가 몰려옵니다.
To escape this negative mood, we immediately start searching for another series to watch.
우리는 이 우울함을 달래려 또 다른 새로운 영상을 찾아 헤맵니다.
This creates a vicious cycle that leaves your brain chronically exhausted and chemically unbalanced.
뇌를 피로하게 만드는 악순환의 고리가 이렇게 완성되는 것입니다.
This constant input of excessive information degrades your brain's capacity for memory and concentration.
과도한 정보 입력은 뇌의 기억과 집중 능력을 떨어뜨리게 됩니다.
Ultimately, what began as relaxing entertainment turns into a state of severe mental exhaustion.
결국 즐거움을 위해 시작한 시청이 정신적 탈진을 부르는 셈이죠.
Now, let us examine how our body's physical movements are affected during these sessions.
이제 몰아보기 동안 우리 신체 움직임에 어떤 일이 일어나는지 알아보겠습니다.
The moment you sit down, the electrical activity in your leg muscles completely shuts off.
우리가 자리에 앉는 순간, 다리 근육의 전기적 활동은 완전히 멈춥니다.
Because your muscles are completely inactive, calorie burning drops to just one calorie per minute.
근육이 일을 하지 않으니 칼로리 소모량은 분당 1칼로리로 떨어지죠.
The production of lipoprotein lipase, an essential enzyme that breaks down fat, drops dramatically.
지방을 분해하는 효소인 '지단백 리파아제'가 급격히 줄어들게 됩니다.
Consequently, levels of harmful fats in your blood rise, causing rapid weight gain.
이로 인해 혈액 속의 유해한 지방 수치와 체중이 증가하게 됩니다.
The blood vessels in your buttocks and back thighs are compressed under your weight.
엉덩이와 허벅지 뒷부분의 혈관들이 몸무게에 짓눌려 수축합니다.
As blood circulation slows down, the returning pressure of blood to your heart weakens.
혈액 순환이 느려지면서 심장으로 돌아가는 혈액의 힘이 약해집니다.
Blood pools in your lower limbs, which often causes your feet and ankles to swell.
다리에 피가 고이면서 발과 발목이 붓는 현상이 발생하게 되죠.
Sitting motionless for hours can cause dangerous blood clots to form in your veins.
장시간 움직이지 않으면 다리 정맥에 피떡인 '혈전'이 생길 수 있습니다.
If these blood clots travel to your lungs, they can cause fatal pulmonary embolism.
이 혈전이 떨어져 나가 폐혈관을 막으면 생명이 위태로워집니다.
A sitting posture places twice as much pressure on your spinal discs as standing.
앉은 자세는 서 있을 때보다 척추에 두 배 이상의 압박을 줍니다.
If you hunch forward to look at the screen, that pressure increases even more.
특히 화면에 몰입하여 몸을 앞으로 굽히면 압박은 훨씬 심해집니다.
When your head tilts forward, your neck bones must bear a heavy extra load.
머리가 앞으로 숙여지면 목뼈는 무려 15킬로그램의 하중을 견뎌야 합니다.
This cumulative pressure from bad posture can eventually cause painful cervical disc herniation.
이 하중이 누적되면 목 디스크가 튀어나오는 심각한 손상을 유발하죠.
The muscles supporting your spine exhaust themselves and eventually become painfully tight and stiff.
허리 주변의 근육들은 척추를 지탱하려다 결국 지쳐서 굳어집니다.
These chronically stiff muscles can pull your pelvis completely out of its natural alignment.
굳어진 근육들은 골반을 뒤틀리게 만들어 체형을 망가뜨립니다.
Joints that remain motionless lose their natural lubricating fluid, leading to early degeneration.
움직임이 없는 관절은 윤활액이 마르면서 뻣뻣하고 아프게 변하죠.
Your body's overall metabolic rate drops, significantly rising the long-term risk of diabetes.
전신의 대사 기능이 가라앉아 당뇨병과 고혈압 위험이 올라갑니다.
Without regular physical use, your large gluteal and thigh muscles slowly waste away over time.
쓰지 않는 엉덩이와 허벅지 근육은 시간이 갈수록 녹아내립니다.
Lacking physical impact, your bones lose density and become increasingly weak and brittle over time.
뼈에 자극이 전달되지 않아 골밀도가 낮아지고 골다공증이 생깁니다.
Lying in awkward positions presses your sciatic nerve, causing severe numbness in legs.
이상한 자세로 오래 누워있으면 좌골신경이 눌려 다리가 저립니다.
Keeping your knees bent for long hours shortens the critical tendons behind your legs.
무릎을 굽힌 채 앉아 있으면 다리 뒷부분의 인대가 짧아집니다.
This muscle tightness is why your whole body feels stiff and painful after watching.
드라마를 다 보고 일어설 때 온몸이 찌푸둥하고 아픈 이유입니다.
A sedentary lifestyle is a silent killer that slowly destroys your entire skeletal system.
앉아만 있는 습관은 우리 뼈를 갉아먹는 조용한 살인자입니다.
Next, let us examine the damage that binge-watching causes to your eyes and brain.
다음으로 몰아보기가 우리의 눈과 뇌에 주는 타격을 알아봅시다.
Digital screens emit high-energy blue light which easily penetrates deep into your visual organs.
디지털 화면에서는 파장이 짧고 에너지가 강한 청색광이 방출됩니다.
This intense blue light directly damages key light-sensitive cells in your retina over time.
이 청색광은 눈의 망막 세포를 직접 공격해 시력을 저하시킵니다.
Staring closely at screens freezes your focusing muscles, causing temporary blurry vision problems later.
가까운 화면만 쳐다보면 모양체 근육이 굳어져 초점 조절이 힘듭니다.
When focusing on a show, your normal blink rate drops by more than half.
화면에 집중할 때 우리의 눈 깜빡임 횟수는 절반 이하로 줄어듭니다.
The protective tear film evaporates quickly, leading to dry eyes and corneal inflammation.
눈물이 빠르게 마르면서 심한 안구건조증과 각막 염증이 생기죠.
Strong glare from the screen overstimulates sensory nerves, causing severe chronic tension headaches.
화면의 강한 불빛은 뇌신경을 자극하여 심한 두통을 유발합니다.
Blue light exposure actively suppresses melatonin, the hormone that tells your body to sleep.
청색광은 수면을 돕는 호르몬인 '멜라토닌'의 생성을 방해합니다.
The brain mistakes artificial screen light for sunshine and remains in a daytime state.
뇌는 화면 불빛을 햇빛으로 착각하여 계속 낮이라고 인식합니다.
Your body's internal biological clock, the circadian rhythm, becomes completely disrupted and misaligned.
몸의 천연 생체시계인 '생체 리듬'이 엉망으로 꼬이게 되죠.
This is why you feel wide awake when trying to sleep after watching.
침대에 누워도 잠이 오지 않고 머릿속이 맑아지는 이유입니다.
While watching television, your brain emits alpha waves, indicating a highly passive state.
텔레비전을 볼 때 뇌는 매우 수동적인 상태인 알파파를 방출합니다.
Critical thinking pathways go dark, while only visual processing regions remain active.
생각하는 회로는 쉬고 오직 시각 정보를 받는 뇌 부위만 일하죠.
If this state continues for long hours, your capacity for logical reasoning gradually weakens.
이 상태가 계속되면 뇌의 논리적 사고 능력이 서서히 약화됩니다.
Watching intense thrillers triggers the release of cortisol, your body's primary stress hormone.
긴장감 넘치는 스릴러물은 스트레스 호르몬인 코르티솔을 높입니다.
Your heart rate accelerates and blood pressure rises, putting your body in constant danger.
심장 박동이 빨라지고 혈압이 상승하여 몸이 비상 상태에 놓입니다.
Even though you are sitting still, your brain and heart remain completely exhausted.
몸은 가만히 있어도 뇌와 심장은 전쟁터에 있는 것처럼 지치게 되죠.
The crucial process of memory consolidation that occurs during deep sleep is severely disrupted.
자는 동안 진행되어야 할 기억 정리 과정이 방해를 받습니다.
You wake up feeling unrefreshed, experiencing what doctors call brain fog next morning.
아침에 일어났을 때 개운하지 않고 뇌가 뿌옇게 느껴집니다.
Binge-watching deprives your brain of essential rest, causing gradual cognitive decline over time.
뇌의 휴식 시간을 빼앗는 몰아보기는 뇌를 서서히 병들게 합니다.
Sleep deprivation caused by late-night viewing completely breaks down your body's immune defenses.
부족한 잠은 우리 몸의 면역 체계를 송두리째 무너뜨립니다.
The activity of lymphocytes, the cells that fight off invading pathogens, drops significantly.
병원균과 싸우는 면역 세포인 '림프구'의 활성도가 급격히 떨어집니다.
When sleep is restricted, your body produces more ghrelin, the hunger-stimulating hormone.
잠이 부족해지면 식욕을 자극하는 호르몬인 '그렐린'이 증가합니다.
Meanwhile, levels of leptin, the hormone that signals fullness, drop sharply in blood.
반면 배부름을 느끼게 하는 '렙틴' 호르몬은 크게 줄어들게 되죠.
This food craving makes you choose high-calorie junk food late at night.
이로 인해 늦은 밤 피자나 치킨 같은 고열량 음식을 갈망합니다.
Eating late and lying down immediately leads to painful acid reflux in esophagus.
밤늦게 음식을 먹고 바로 누우면 역류성 식도염이 생기기 쉽습니다.
Since metabolism slows down at night, most consumed calories are stored as fat.
밤에는 신진대사가 느려져 섭취한 칼로리가 대부분 지방으로 쌓입니다.
This pattern leads to abdominal obesity and builds dangerous visceral fat around organs.
이는 복부 비만을 유발하고 장기를 압박하는 내장지방이 됩니다.
Hormonal disruption and fat accumulation raise insulin resistance, eventually causing type-two diabetes.
호르몬 교란과 지방 축적은 인슐린 저항성을 높여 당뇨를 부릅니다.
Every hour spent watching a screen is an hour lost for healthy exercise.
몰아보기 시간만큼 우리는 운동하고 움직일 시간을 잃어버립니다.
Staying isolated in your room reduces real-life social interactions and real human connection.
방 안에 홀로 갇혀 있으면 사람들과의 교류가 차단되어 고립되죠.
This social isolation increases feelings of loneliness and worsens overall symptoms of depression.
사회적 고립은 외로움을 키우고 우울증 증상을 더욱 심화시킵니다.
Does this mean we should never watch our favorite dramas again for life?
그렇다면 우리는 좋아하는 드라마를 평생 보지 말아야 할까요?
Absolutely not! The key is establishing healthy habits to maintain your body's balance.
당연히 아닙니다! 핵심은 신체의 균형을 지키는 건강한 습관입니다.
Every time an episode ends, stand up and stretch your entire body thoroughly.
매 편이 끝날 때마다 자리를 털고 일어나 기지개를 켜십시오.
For eye health, follow the twenty-twenty-twenty rule and look at distant objects regularly.
눈 건강을 위해 이십 분마다 이십 피트 먼 곳을 이십 초간 보세요.
Decide on a viewing limit beforehand and set a loud timer to stop.
시청 시작 전에 미리 시간을 정해두고 타이머를 맞추는 게 좋습니다.
Always activate the blue light filter on your devices during evening viewing sessions.
저녁 시간 이후에는 화면의 청색광 차단 필터를 꼭 활성화하세요.
Try riding an indoor bicycle or doing light squats while watching your show.
화면을 보면서 실내 자전거를 타거나 가벼운 스쿼트를 해보세요.
Choose warm herbal tea or water instead of sugary sodas for night snacks.
늦은 밤 간식은 탄산음료 대신 따뜻한 차나 물을 선택하세요.
Keep all electronic devices away from your bed at least one hour before sleeping.
잠들기 최소 한 시간 전에는 전자기기를 침대에서 멀리 치우세요.
Go outside on weekends to soak up sunlight and gently stimulate your bones.
주말에는 야외로 나가 햇빛을 받으며 가볍게 뼈를 자극해야 합니다.
Our bones and nerves stay healthy in direct proportion to how much we move.
우리 몸의 뼈와 신경은 정직하게 우리가 움직이는 만큼 건강해집니다.
Protect your precious bones and eyes by practicing smart and balanced viewing habits.
현명한 시청 습관으로 소중한 뼈와 눈의 건강을 꼭 지켜내세요.